Hello. Good afternoon. Keep coming in. So, welcome. Thank you for coming along to this
session. My name is Steve. I'm a Microsoft MVP,
Plurusite author and engineer at Elastic. You can find me online. I'm at Steve J. Gordon
on most social platforms. I blog at SteveJ Gordon.co.uk. Some of the stuff that I'll be
going through today is kind of built off of longer form blog posts. So, if you want to dive
a bit deeper, check out those articles. This bit link here. If you want access to the slides,
the code and things after the session, just grab that link with the QR code there and you'll
be able to kind of review those. I'll share that link again at the end. So, today we're
going to be talking about high performance C-shop code and some of the, I call them new.
They're not new anymore, but newer features available to us in the language and the
base class libraries that allow us to do high performance code. So, just to set the agenda
and make sure we're all on the same page. What we'll be covering is we're going to begin
with just a quick discussion around what is performance and what is it we're actually
aiming to improve in our code. Thank you. We'll then spend a little bit of time talking
about how to actually measure the performance of code so that we know where we're starting
from and where we're actually moving towards as we do some optimizations on some code.
We'll then spend a bit of time with these types. So, span of T, we don't know span and memory of T.
We'll talk a bit about a rapes. We'll talk a little bit about pipeline system IO pipelines
and a type we'll read only sequence. And hopefully there'll be time for me to race through some
stuff on System Text Jason at the end and just show some demos of using high performance stuff
there. So, let's begin really with the aspects of performance. So, there's three main
sort of categories or criteria of performance that I tend to think about when I'm optimizing
code. The first is execution time. So, how long does a unit of code take to run? That might be,
you know, the entire operation of handling a request, for example, or it might be that you're
looking at smaller units of code, individual methods, or even lines of code, and how long
those take to execute. Typically, if we can make our code execute more quickly, then we can give
a better response to the user, the customer that's visiting the site, or using the application,
because we're able to return results or information to them more quickly.
Frueput is a sort of related measure, but it's a better way of thinking about this in terms of
what a system or a service can actually achieve. So, Frueput is more a measure of what we can actually
do with a given amount of resource on a machine. So, request per second in ASP Connect core,
maybe messages, processed off a cube per second per minute, however we're measuring that.
And this gives us a nice way of measuring sort of the actual performance of an application
in production, because it's an easy measure that we can take using metrics-based tools to collect
this information to see how applications are performing. These two are quite closely linked.
Typically, if we can reduce the execution time of our code, then we might see that we're able
to increase the Frueput of the system as well. It's not always an exact correlation.
Different things can affect Frueput. There's different sort of bottlenecks that you might encounter
on your system around IO and memory that may sort of play a part in that measure as well.
But typically, if we get the execution time, we see improvements in Frueput. And then the final one,
that not everyone tends to think about, is around memory allocations. So, allocations in .NET
are extremely cheap, because we already have the heap memory sort of ready to go. And so, when we
create a new object, it's usually just bumping a pointer logically within that sort of heap memory.
The cost for memory allocations comes later. At some point in time, those objects go out of scope,
and that memory can be reclaimed. So, at some point, garbage collection process is going to need to
kick in and clean up those unused objects. And that tends to have a small, but sometimes significant
performance impact in high Frueput systems. And so, if we can avoid allocating objects on the heap
and allocating memory at all, then we avoid that potential penalty later on. And a lot of the stuff
you see, if you read any of the post-partly, like Stephen Taub from Microsoft, when they talk about
the high performance features that they've introduced, they'll often be demonstrating how they've
reduced allocations as one of the ways that they've made performance overall better.
Now, I do like to caution that performance is contextual. There's various different ways of saying
this, but I just sort of summarise this in this form. Because a lot of what I'm going to show you
today isn't necessarily stuff that you need to race to your office on Monday and start implementing.
But in certain situations where you've got high Frueput systems or you're already encountering
certain bottlenecks in your system, then you might want to start looking at optimizing some of the
code to reduce those problems that you're facing. But maybe for 95% of applications, some of the
stuff I'm going to show you today might not be necessary. Although, what I do hope to demonstrate
is that some of the techniques, for example, reduce allocations don't necessarily require a lot of
deep advanced code to write them. Sometimes we can actually achieve those gains with relatively
simple changes. That said, there is a bit of a trade-off when it comes to high performance code.
Typically, the high performance code tends to get a little bit more verbose. It's a little less
easy maybe to read or reason about because it's written in a certain way that we know optimises
for certain scenarios. That can mean that it's harder to maintain the code that we've moved to
this higher performance environment. You do have to have this trade-off. If you're working on a
system that's regularly changing, it has lots of developers touching that code on a regular basis,
then you might want to move more towards readability and maintainability as your priority,
because actually getting out features, shipping code is more important than milliseconds of execution
time or small amounts of memory gains that you might make. But there will always be a certain set
of applications where if you can reduce the memory footprint, for example, of the application,
you might be able to reduce costs in terms of how you have to scale that application
in production environment. You need to weigh this up in your organisation service by service to
see where you should be treading across this line. Are you moving more to the high performance
or are you needing to just keep that code easy to work on and easy to read?
When we go around optimising code, I'm going to be demonstrating what I refer to as the
optimisation cycle today. The most important first step in optimising code is actually making
measurements first. It's very dangerous when you're doing optimisations to make assumptions about
how code might operate if we switch to a higher performance code that we've already used,
maybe elsewhere, it doesn't always pay off in the way we expect. We start by measuring our code
to get an understanding of what the system is currently doing. The very first set of measurements
should be, ideally, production measurements if you can. How is your system currently function
if it's already deployed? What is your throughput of a web server, for example, or how many messages
can your processing service manage off a queue in a certain given amount of time? You want to make
sure that any changes you're making on negatively affecting those production metrics.
Then when we start actually looking at where we should be spending our time in our code,
we want to start with higher level tools that allow us to profile CPU and memory to start to give us
a guidance of where we want to start optimising code. We'll talk about a few of the tools in a
moment, but the basic idea is we want to know what are the hot pass in the application so that we
can go and focus on where we could approve that code base on those hot pass. That's going to give
us the most gain if it's code that's executed most often. We can use memory profiles, for example,
to help us narrow down within that hot pass where are the potential gains for maybe reducing
allocations coming from. Then we go down to even lower level measurements. We'll have a look at
an example of benchmarking with a tool called benchmark.net as we move through the session. This
is what allows us to get very high precision measurements for small units of code as we go about
optimising it. We measure first, we get our sort of baselines and then we can begin to optimise.
The most important thing about this step is that we don't just make all of the possible
changes that we can think of in one go. I prefer to do this in small iterations, small changes.
After we optimise maybe a few lines of code with a high performance technique, maybe like one of
the ones I'll show you today, we want to measure again to validate that that change is actually
represented in the data that we're seeing. If you change a whole bunch of things together,
you might improve the overall performance of your code, but you don't know if all of those changes
were actually positive. By doing things in small increments, you can get very scientific about
validating each theory that you have and each change that you're making is pushing you towards
whatever goal it is you're working towards. Then this cycle just continues. There's no real specific
end point for this that you have to determine within your organisation, within your team what is
the point to stop optimising. Sometimes you'll have reached your given requirement, you may have
reduced your memory footprint by half and you're happy. That's fine, that's a good place to stop
if that was your objective. Sometimes you might just hit the ceiling of what you think you can
reasonably achieve. You've gone through all of the techniques that you've read about or seen
today and actually you don't think there's any more real gains you're talking sort of nanoseconds
or maybe a few bites here and there, but there's not a real gain to be had. So you don't want to
continue optimising too far past that sort of optimum point of time spent versus the gains that
you're making. So how do we measure high performance code, how do we sort of start to analyse some of
this stuff? So the first tool I like to highlight just because it's often overlooked is if you're using
Visual Studio and I do, then the diagnostic tools that pop up when you start debugging an application
can be quite useful. They can give you a bit of a representative view of how the memory profile
of that application is looking. You can see where the GCs are occurring. You can take snapshots
of that memory if you want to understand a little bit more about it. And so just by sort of debugging
our application we have access to some rich data. The caution here is that you are in a debug mode.
You're not running this against highly optimised code. So there might be some differences to what
you would measure in a production application. So it's a good indicator but it isn't necessarily
a final measure. For that what you want to do is start going a little bit deeper on the
the release build code and actually use tools like the Visual Studio Profiling Suite or Perfew or
some of the JetRains products to actually narrow down further. Visual Studio Profiling tools are
actually pretty rich today. We have a lot of options in there. We can look at all of the memory
allocations, tracking those across time to see what's being allocated. We can profile the CPU and
see where the method times are being spent. And we can also dig into things like the Async and the
Task Parallel Library parts as well. So you can actually get quite rich information just from Visual
Studio. The other end of the scale I would say is Perfew. This is a very rich tool, it's a very
advanced tool. I don't get along with it particularly well. I've dipped in and out of it but it is
quite difficult to get to grips with. And so I don't recommend it as kind of the first thing you
go to unless you really feel you need to or you've had some familiarity with it in the past. Where I
tend to push most of my time for performance stuff is into the JetRains tools. I'm not paid to
say that. I don't work for them. I just prefer them. .trace.memory are both very easy tools to get
started with in terms of taking CPU profiles of an application as well as understanding where the
memory is being allocated and diving into that information. So pick the tool that you like.
Sometimes not always, it can be useful to go quite deep. And this is where maybe you might
want to start even looking at the intermediate language code that gets generated when you compile
your C-sharp application. Sometimes this can give you a rid of an indicator in terms of the C-sharp
you're writing. How many IL intermediate language instructions is that actually compiling down to?
And typically if you can make your code smaller and have less instructions, then it's going to
execute more quickly. Other things we can sometimes spot in IL based tools is we can see where
boxing instructions, for example, are being occurring. So we can maybe identify cases where we're
boxing value types as well. So not always needed, but there are various free tools out there that you
can use just to go and inspect that IL code. And don't overlook the importance of having production
metrics and monitoring in place before you start doing this as well. Again, testing this stuff
locally, even if you try your hardest, you might not always get a representative example of how
an application performs in a real production environment. Because our developer machines are a
bit different. There's no real contention going on. The loads that we're putting through them are
typically not necessarily going to be the same as we would see in production. And the patterns
of usage might differ as well. So having monitoring in production for existing applications before
you start this journey is pretty useful. Just basic things like maybe measures of memory, CPU,
usage, throughput of an application, if it's an ASP and ECOR type app, can be really useful. Because
you can see if you're positively or negatively affecting them in the direction that you hope you are.
So the tool that we will spend a little bit of time with today just because less people are
familiar with it is benchmark.net. So this is a library for typically micro-bent remarking our code.
So this is where we all want to measure small chunks of code, maybe individual methods,
maybe even individual lines of code, and compare them to how they're sort of working after we've
optimised them. It's a highly precise tool. So it does a lot of things to give us accurate
measurements. Technically you could just use like a stopwatch or a timer around some code,
and that would give you a rough measure. But what benchmark.net is doing is it's going to run
many different stages as it goes through benchmarking. It does a warm up phase to make sure that the
code you're testing is pre-gitted so that the just-in-time compiler has run for its very
tiered compilation levels and your code is the most optimal that it would be in a real scenario.
It runs its own overhead measurements, so it checks how it's overhead of actually inspecting
and monitoring. Your application while it's running might take into effect, and it can remove that
overhead. And then it will run each of your benchmark methods, many tens, hundreds,
thousands of times, to make sure it's giving you good statistical averages for the data that you're
measuring. So when we start getting down to those kind of nanosecond tiny measurements of time,
we need that highly precise measurement process to make sure that what we're getting is accurate.
There's various other pieces of data that we can collect in the form of diagnoses. So we'll see one
in action shortly, but these are things like GCN memory. So we can change the GC modes that we're
running our benchmarks under. We can look at different JIT modes and things, and this can be useful.
Sometimes we can then replicate more closely what would be a production system when we're doing our
benchmarking. We can prepare for performance on all the different platforms as well, so you might
be developing on a Windows machine, but you might be running your benchmarks against Linux mode as
well, and you can run these then in CI and compare how those things run. This tool is the tool that's
very extensive of use by the Microsoft Teams. You'll see it in all of Stephen Talb's annual performance
blog posts, and it's been used heavily through the .NET runtime code base as well as ASP in
a core as the teams have been optimizing those. So this is kind of the hello world of benchmarking.
So up the top here we start with a main method, and that's just invoking this benchmark runner.run
method. And in this case, what we're doing is passing in a type that contains some benchmarks.
Now there's various different ways that you can configure benchmark.NET to run. You can have it
in kind of an interactive mode where it does discover all of your benchmarks in the system and let
you choose what you run. You can have it in a more CLI mode where you, if you're doing it,
sort of CI environments and you want to run specific benchmarks, you can do that by passing in the name
of those as arguments. But in this mode, we're just going to run everything that's in that class
below. The name, pars, or benchmarks. And what I've added here is that memory diagnoses attribute,
which allows us to say that in addition to execution time measurements, we want to do a run that
measures the allocation overhead of this code as well. I have a little bit of setup code here,
so these are set up as constant or static pieces of data. They're not things that I'm actually
measuring as part of my benchmark, but they're things I need to do the benchmark. So I need some
input data and I need an instance of a name, parser. And then my actual benchmark is below. So it's
just a regular method with the benchmark attribute applied to it. And in this case, we're calling
the get last name method of that parser, parsing in a full name, and we're going to then see what the
execution time and memory overhead of that particular method is. We're going to run this. It's
going to take some time to run. You want to do it on a release build. You also ideally want to do it
on a system that's not running other stuff. So in an ideal world, you disable every other application,
even maybe antivirus, because all of those things could kick in and affect nanosecond level measurements.
But generally, as long as you've turned off most of the other apps that could consume memory or
maybe jump in and affect CPU scheduling and things, you'll get fairly accurate results. And after
a few minutes, because of all those warm up phases, all of those many executions that it will do,
we end up with this basic summary results. And there's a much richer set of results that you can
pull from the output folder. But in this case, what it's giving is a quick summary of that particular
method takes 116 nanoseconds to run. We don't know if that's good, bad, it's pretty fast, but
could we make it quicker? Do we need to make it quicker? That's a decision for us to decide later on.
Because we added the memory diagnoses, we have a few extra columns on the end. So in this case,
we have a single column for Gen 0, which is a rough approximation as best it can kind of estimate of
how many per 1000 operations, how many Gen 0 collections would be incurred. So in this case, we're
saying that you'd have to run that method roughly 29,000 times to have induced enough pressure
of Gen 0 objects for that to then need freeing. It's not an exact measure because the GC uses a bunch
of heuristics and sort of adaptive technologies behind the scenes to try and make it as efficient as
possible. But it gives you a bit of an indication. And the fact that we're not seeing a Gen 1 or Gen 2
column here shows us that none of our objects are long lived or particularly large necessarily.
We can see how many bytes was actually allocated as a result of calling that method. Again,
we don't know if this is good or bad, but we do know that we've got 144 bytes allocated
by this particular method. So this would be a good starting point for us.
So now that we've had a brief introduction to sort of benchmark code, let's look at some
high performance code. And then I'll hopefully show you some demonstrations of where I've applied
that in the past and how I've made those gains pay off for me. So the first type I want to
spend probably most time on is span of T. I'm always curious, how many people in the room would say
that they've heard of this span of T concept already? I'll show you hands. Maybe half-ish.
How many people have used span of T in their own code base so far? It's not bad, but far fewer. And
that's, I've been doing this talk on and off for probably four or five years now. And it's
pretty much always the same proportion. A lot of people have heard of span of T or a reasonable
number because it's always mentioned in things like those annual blog posts by Stephen Talb,
it's always mentioned quite heavily in any post that discusses performance in relation to
.NET and the runtime based class libraries. Because it was quite a revolutionary addition to
.NET that has led to many improvements to the runtime that we've seen in precincts.NET sort of
free one sort of timeframe. But I also find that not many people have actually used it in code,
partly because they may not need to, but also partly because I think Microsoft tended to caution
away from using it. And I've always been a little bit less on the caution side. It's not
hugely complex to get started with span of T and you can apply it quite easily in a code base is
to reduce allocations as we'll see. So this was built in .NET Core 2.1 and since then. So we've
got it on all latest versions of .NET sort of runtime. It's also available as a system memory
package. So you can actually use this with .NET framework applications and netstandard libraries.
There is a subtle difference in the level of performance. So in .NET Core, what they did is
actually make some runtime changes to optimize for this type in the best way possible. We don't
tend to see runtime changes in .NET framework partly because it's mostly maintenance mode and
partly because of fears around how that ships. With .NET Core, we have a much easier system of
upgrading and running side by side versions. And so they felt safe in actually optimizing this
with actual runtime changes. And it's hard what it does. It provides a read right view over some
contiguous region of memory. The nice thing about span of T is it's kind of agnostic to what
that memory is. So we can actually use this over traditional heap allocated memory. So things
like strings or arrays, which are contiguous blocks of memory off the heap. But we can also use
it to reference memory that's allocated directly on the stack. And even native and unmanaged
memory if you're working in those types of environments. But we work with this one type that's
both type safe and memory safe in all of those scenarios. So one of the key things it offers to us
is this ability to avoid allocations and data copying, which can be quite significant in reducing
the overhead of application code. So we can work with it in a very similar way to traditional array
based data structures. We can index into it. We can iterate through that data. There's pretty much
almost no overhead versus using a native array. And all of the operations on here have been highly
optimized to be as efficient as possible, which is why it's used throughout the runtime libraries.
One of the key operations on span that's the most valuable really is this idea of slicing data
or slicing memory. So here what we do is we start by creating a new integer array of nine elements.
And then we call our span on there to get a span of T, a span of int in this case over that data.
And so these two local variables here would point to the same portion of memory.
The first thing you might worry about is this creation of this span of int that we're creating as a
result of that new as span call. The thing about span is it isn't ever allocated on the heap. So
there's never any GC overhead from creating an instance of a span. It's a specialized type that
only ever appears on the stack. And we'll see later why that introduces some limitations.
But it also offers this guarantee that actually it's a very cheap thing to do. There's never any
heap costs that we should be worrying about. Now once we have that span based view over the data,
any point in time we can call slice on there to give us a different view over that same block of
memory. So in this case we're slicing in to a starting position of two in a length of five.
And so this new span to here references a different portion of the existing memory. We haven't
done any data copying. We've just changed our view. And this is extremely powerful if you're
processing bytes that may be a streaming off the wire or you're processing through large strings,
which are just, you know, ultimately just characters in a system. Because you can just change your
view over that data very quickly. The nice thing about slicing isn't constant time, constant cost
operation as well. So it doesn't matter if this array is nine elements or nine million. The
cost of slicing into it for any length is pretty much exactly the same each time. And that makes
it very powerful because we're never copying anything. We're basically just holding a pointer
within that memory portion. And then the length, that's pretty easy to maintain.
The analogy I use for slicing, if it hasn't quite sort of fit into your mental model yet, is of
maybe taking some photographs. So I've been out in Porto. We've been taking some photographs
around the city. And sometimes there might be a building or some piece of architecture that we
want to get a nice close up picture of. And one option we have is to walk closer to the object.
And once we're close to it, we can take our photo. And depending on how far away that object is,
it might have taken us a fair amount of time, a fair amount of energy to get there. But eventually,
we will get our close up. The alternative on our phone is that we just pinched in and ignoring the
fact that we have, you know, potentially some degradation of image quality that doesn't come
across in this analogy. The key thing there is a pinch zoom is pretty much a constant time,
constant cost operation. We can very quickly change our field of view over a scene. And then we
have a different view of that same scene from the same position with very low effort. And that's
kind of the idea we're slicing. So I'm going to begin with a brief overview of what it looks
like to optimize some code. Now this particular example, as you caution, is very contriot, very trivial.
This is just to get us started. And then we'll look at some real world code later on.
So let's imagine, on Monday, you return to work and your manager tells you that if
the somehow that they found a way that if you could have a method that takes an array of elements,
even number of elements, and then starts taking a quarter of those elements from the middle,
you're going to have some major business advantage over your competitor. So let's imagine that's
the scenario you're given. One pretty reasonable way that you could achieve that without thinking too
hard is, okay, well, we'll get the length, we'll skip halfway into that array, we'll take the number
of elements or quarter of the elements, and then we'll return the new array. And that's perfectly
valid code. It will do the job. But then maybe your manager comes to you and says, actually, if we
can make this code really, really fast, maybe we can make a huge amount of money. So I told you
it's contrived, but let's go with this. So the first thing we should do in this scenario is measure.
Before we even begin optimizing, we want to start with measuring our current assumption.
And so what we do here in this benchmark is there's a few new elements that I'll introduce. Again,
it's still a class, but this time we've got this size property on here with the Prams attribute
with three different values. What this lets us say to benchmark.net is that we want to run these
benchmarks with these three different values for that size property. So run these benchmarks three
times essentially with those different sizes. And this allows us to kind of test edge cases.
Sometimes testing your kind of expected value is fine, but maybe there are edge cases to what
your system accepts that actually might result in different measures of performance. And so by
testing your kind of middle case plus your edge cases, you can get make sure that you've got a
representative view that the changes apply in all scenarios. Because we're setting this up,
we now need an array of these different lengths as our input. And so what we do in this global setup
method here, which is just a regular method with the global setup attribute, we can pre-create that
array of the right size and populate it. This runs once for the benchmark run actually kicks in,
so there's no measurement overhead here. This isn't part of what you're measuring as part of your
benchmark. It's just setup code. And then to do the benchmark, we can just run that piece of code
that we saw earlier. The only difference from what we looked at earlier is that we're now putting
this baseline equals true to say this is our starting point. And once we run this, we see that
okay, for an input array of 100 elements, it's about 100 nanoseconds, 224 bytes allocated,
and we see what we'd kind of expect even to code. If we reason about it, as we increase the
input array size, then by factors, the execution time and the allocations are going up, because we're
creating a newer array at the end of the day without new data in it. And so that's giving us our
starting point, our baseline. So maybe the first theory we have is, well, we've heard that Link
has some overhead to it, and maybe we should avoid using that, and that will make our lives better.
So in this case, what we do is create a new array pre-sized. We then use a array copy
to copy the data from one array to the other, and then we see if this works better. So we run our
benchmarks again, now with our new version added. And we can see that for 100 elements, it looks
pretty good. We've reduced our execution time by about 86%. And it looks like our allocation
ratio is improving massively as well, by 43. The good thing is we've tested other sizes here,
and we can see that while the execution time is still a good improvement, the allocation ratio
is getting less than that's valuable. And that's because all we've done is remove the small 96 bytes
of overhead of using that link expression versus what we're doing with the array copy approach.
But we're still creating a new array, we're still copying data in there. So in this final example,
let's assume that we can change the return type. So I'm changing the return type here to the
span of int. So let's assume that there's further processing that happens after this occurs,
and our callers can accept a span of int back. So in this case, we now use the as span, and then we
can slice in. You can also use the range operator here if you prefer the syntax, so you don't need to
slice. You can just do square braces dot dot length, and that's quite nice as well, or starting
position and in position. And so in this example, we now move to kind of a span based approach,
and we'll see that now the execution time is 99% improved, so we're less than an anno second,
which I think most people will agree is pretty reasonable. And the allocation overhead now is zero.
We've not got any bytes allocated, because all we're doing is returning a new view over that
existing array from that stop position halfway in for that length of the call to the elements.
And we can see that as we move through the different sizes, this constant time, constant cost
operation of slicing doesn't matter how big that input array is, the savings are the same.
And so this is now massively reduced that portion of codes overhead.
As I say, a little contrived, but we'll get to some better examples soon.
Now the other nice thing we can do with span is we can work with strings. So on a string literal,
or a string variable, we can call as span, and we get back a read only span of char.
So char is fairly obvious. Strings are made up of characters. The read only span,
because the runtime will enforce the safety here that strings are immutable. So it's never
going to allow us to get a read write view with a span over the memory occupied by a string,
because that would let us effectively mutate that string's data, and that would break pretty
much every assumption we have in our code base about safety of strings. So we get back a read only view.
And so this still is useful, because we can pass through the existing strings,
finding the pieces of data that we want. So in this, again, very basic example, maybe we just want
to get the portion of that string that represents the surname, so that we can do some further analysis
on it. In this case, we could say, let's find the index of the last space character, and then slice
from that position onwards. And now we're still working with the same block of memory, but we're
able to do it on strings as well. Now there are some limitations of span of T that are worth
pointing out. And as I go through these, you might get more and more concerned about where this
look can actually be applied, but don't worry, it is fine. So the first thing is, I mentioned earlier
that the guarantee that we have that a span is never going to end up on the heap, so we can use
it safely at any point in our code without worrying about heap allocations. And that's enforced by
the fact that it's not just a normal struct, it's actually got this ref struct keyword that was
introduced in C-shop 7.2, that enables a kind of guarantee that the runtime will enforce that
this type can never end up on the heap, because there's various ways that a value type would end up
there. And so what this effectively means is we can't ever let a span of byte or a span of
int or whatever it is be boxed, because that would be then stored on the heap. One of the main
reasons for this limitation, this kind of stack only limitation, is that it can be pointing at
stack allocated memory, so we can never allow this span of T thing to live longer than the stack
frame that it is built, is used on, because it might then be pointing at data that's no longer valid
if it outlives that stack frame. So that's one of the reasons we can't do boxing. It also means that
it can't be used as a field in a class or a non-ref struct, because again that data is living on the heap.
This is the one that tends to trip people up, because of the way that async works,
it can't be used as an argument or a local variable in async methods, because async methods behind
the scenes eventually get compiled down to that state machine that you may or may not sort of be
aware of, but on most code that will be a struct, but it's still not a struct that's guaranteed to be
stack only. And so for the same reasons that it can't be a field in a class, it can't be used in
those environments, because it those basically get hoisted up as fields on that state machine object
that gets created. For a very similar reason it can't be captured by lambda expressions because of
the closure that would be created around those. And up until this version of .NET that's coming
sort of in November, it couldn't be used as a generic type of argument. Now that's actually being,
that limitation is being removed, because we're getting this new sort of now new combination of
keywords as a where constraint on generics where we can say we do allow a ref struct, as long as we
know that our method is never going to let that escape the safety, the safe context of being within
the same stack frame. And so in C-shop 13 you can start to use it in certain new environments.
And there's other limitations I'm not even starting to hint at here that get much more
sort of deeper about how this functions. But the key thing is that we'll ask some limitations to
it. Fortunately at the same time as you're introducing span, the team introduced this other type
called memory of T, which has very similar semantics to span. The main difference though is it
can live on the heap if it needs to. So it's defined in a different way, which does make it a little
less versatile because you can't necessarily point it at stack allocated memory anymore.
And the performance is not quite as good. There's certain guarantees about the stack only nature of
span that have allowed the runtime to be modified to make it highly efficient. And we don't get all
of those same guarantees with this memory T version. So it's defined in the code as a read-only
struct but not a rest struct. So we still generally don't see it being copied too often hopefully,
but it might eventually end up being boxed in certain scenarios. Because of that if we're working
with it directly, then it's going to be slightly slower if we do things like slicing into it.
But fortunately at any point in time we can call span on there and get the span property, which
represents the span-based portion of the same block of memory. And so this kind of comes into effect
if we're trying to do something in say an async method, and we'd really like to take some data in
in this new sort of highly optimized form. If we try and pile up a span of byte here, then we get
this compiler error because we're now trying to create this parameter of a type span. But what we
can do instead is switch our code to accept a memory of byte and we're still fine. And things like a
byte array, etc., will implicitly convert to this quite happily. And that means that we could
just work with that memory directly. If we're not worried about the final nanosecond of performance,
then usually working with memory is reasonable. But if you want to, what you can do is create
a non-async method where you can accept a span and then switch to that at any point in your code
that you can do so. Typically we're only in an async context during some IO operation. We're
getting some bytes off the wire through a stream or we're reading in a file or whatever it might be.
But once we've done that sort of initial read and we've got some data buffered into memory somewhere,
at that point we can switch to non-async code while we're processing. And so in this code base,
one option you might attempt to do is try and create an instance of a span sliced at a certain
point that you're going to pass into that async, non-async method, which again you can't do because
it can't be a local. But what we can do is pass in that slice expression directly and the
compiler is totally happy that it can make all the right guarantees about this now. And then that
non-async method can do all of the processing using the high performance span based approach.
And we can switch back to the async method when we're done.
So I'm going to start putting this into practice with a more real world example.
And this is based on something for a project I worked on at a previous company.
So I'm going to switch over to Visual Studio, which looks okay there. It's the code okay at the back
for everyone. Good. Cool. So what I'm going to do is show you, I'll give you the quick summary of
what this is doing actually. I'll show you this slide. So the context for this service,
which is a microservice I used to work on, is that we were reading messages of a key. In this case,
it was Amazon SQLS. We de-serialized that JSON data from the key. And we wanted them to store it
into the Amazon S3 blob store a copy of that message, basically as a backup process. And in order
to ensure that we were only storing one copy, we derived a unique object key, basically a file name
for that blob from some of the properties on the message. And so the existing code that we had
looked a bit like this, this is sort of simplified down a bit, but we have this event context, which
you can imagine represents the de-serialized message coming in. In this case, it's got five properties
in the real system. It has a few hundred. But the key thing is we wanted to use just a few of
those for the object key. So if the date was present, we'd use the date, but it wasn't always
guaranteed, hence why this code deals with that possibility. But the main way this code worked
is that we basically created a string array to hold all of the parts that were going to be used in
that object key. And then for each index of that string array, we used this get part method
to take the input string. So in this case, for example, this is coming from the product or the
site key that's coming off that object. That would come in, if it was null or empty, then we would
just fill that particular element we've just unknown because for some reason we didn't have the data.
Otherwise, we'd call remove spaces, which just did a replace of spaces with underscores.
And then once we've done that, we did this is valid, check basically using rejects to make
sure that it matched a particular set of characters when you were safe for a history object keys.
So we did that with all of the main pieces of data coming in. We then used the date time
two string just to form it out the date if it was present. And then we put the message ID in a
suffix on that file. So once we've got all of the individual pieces, we just used string join to
join them together, lowercase everything, and that then became the object key. So a few of you might
have already spotted where that might allocate and why that could potentially be optimized.
And so I'll show you the new code up here. So there's a few differences. So this code has been
updated for like dotnet eight. And so one of the things that I did in here was move to the new
source generated reject stuff, which basically pre-computes the rejects expressions and the code needed
to do a rejects match in an optimal way. And it does it at compile time rather than run time.
So you can remove some of the runtime cost of rejects by using it.
The other thing it does here is use this kind of special sort of technique for basically defining
these read only span static properties. And what this does is the compiler knows how to handle this
and basically treats this as specialized data that gets stored into the actual binary data for the
DLL. And so at any time that we're using these in code, it's just pointing to an existing memory
location within that DLL, which lets us be very optimal and avoid allocating those when we're comparing.
The main bulk of the code then use this new string create feature. So basically what string
create lets us do is to pre-allocate some memory on the heap that's going to be used to create a
string. But it lets us mutate that memory directly and work with it as a span while we're creating
the string. So once it's created, it becomes a regular immutable string. But during that creation
method, the code actually can mutate the various bytes or various characters within that.
So in order for that to work, it has to pre-compute the length because we need to know the right length
that we need for that string to occupy. I won't show you that code, it's fairly boring. But then we do
string create. And what string create takes is this key builder action, which is this special span
action type that basically gives us, let's have passed in our state, which is our event context.
And it gives us access to a span here, a span of characters, which is that pre-allocated
heap memory for the string. And so in here what we do is for each of those pieces of data that we
want to use in the string key, we call build part. And we pass in a current position as we do this,
which is what's going to allow us to slice through that memory as we're adding new elements to it.
And so we take the input string and we do basically what the original code is. But we're now doing a
more sort of basic check to see if it's null or empty by checking if it's the length of zero or
white space. We then run the source generated rejects for the validation piece. We then call this
memory extensions to low invariant, which lets us take a string, copy the characters out and
lowercase them into our span pre-allocated memory in one operation. Every time we do something
where we're writing, we're incrementing our position by how much we've written. So we're slowly
moving through that span of memory as we add more elements to it. And basically we do this for each
item. Then up here we do a string, sorry, a span replace. So this new replace operation added in
.NET 8 is very optimized way of replacing certain characters within a span. So we replace all the
spaces with underscores. For dates we can use this new tri format or newer tri format method, which
lets us format a date directly into again a span of characters. And gives us back how many bytes we're
written as doing that. We then lowercase the message ID and we copy on that JSON suffix. And in
this case we're just slicing, in this case using a range based operator for the last five characters
where we put the suffix in that. So what this is doing is basically moving us to a span based
way of building up that string. Now I promise we benchmarked and we did all the right things as we
went ahead with this. And I'll just show you the results so you can kind of see the gains.
So with the new code we were about 26% quicker. Actually our improvements were like three times faster
when we did this back in the free one days. I've updated this code a few times to move to new
versions of .NET and Microsoft keep improving even those built in operations like string replace
for example. So the gain is going down but there's still a gain to be had by manually doing this.
And the key thing is that we then removed about 74% of the allocations. So we're down to 192 bytes.
And when we would profile the memory that 192 bytes was the actual object key string that we
were creating and we had to create to pass into the Amazon S3 API. So that means that we've
got rid of all the overhead of creating that. We're just down to the actual cost of the string
creation that we actually want. Now on its own this might not seem like it's worthwhile. It's a
few hundred bytes, right? But this service was doing 18 million messages a day. So this one
subtle change to the code based in how we manage this object key creation saved us 10 gig of daily
allocations. And that's going to contribute to a number of GCs that we're no longer having to
do in that application as a result. So we got quite a nice gain there. So the next type I want to
talk about is called ArrayPool. The name kind of gives us one away. It's a pool of arrays.
And this can be used anywhere in your code based where you need those kind of like temporary
buffers of either bytes or characters as you're doing some processing. Typically where we see this is
if we're doing anything within an iteration where we might be working with stream based data where
we have to pass it a temporary buffer to work with. And what we can use the RrayPool to do is
instead of incurring the cost of those temporary arrays each time we're doing that processing work,
we can use a rented array which is coming from this shared pool to avoid that sort of cost. So
over time we sort of amortize away the cost of creating those temporary buffers. So it's found in
the system buffers name space. Renting is pretty straightforward. We access the array pool of T. So
whatever the type we want an array to hold. We generally use this shared version. So this is a
pre-built sort of in the box implementation of an array pool that uses a predefined set of
buckets for the sizes of the arrays that it can store. And then we just rent the one that we want
with the length we need. The key thing is that we might and generally we'll get an array that's
larger than what we ask for. And the reason is for a pool to be useful it has to bucket into
particular sizes. It can't have every possible size array that we might ever need because the
chances of us needing the same exact size every time isn't necessarily consistent. So it's going
to give us the closest array size it has that's at least big enough to hold what we've asked for.
Which means that when we're working with an array pool based piece of data we're typically
then going to need to track the length of the data that we've actually written into that temporary
buffer so that we can always slice it later on and just view the portion that we know we've written.
When we're done we return it, we return the array and we optionally can pass this clear array
switch here as well. So by default the clear array is set to false which does mean that by default
when you return an array the data is still left in there as it was when you worked with it before.
So for sensitive systems that might be something you need to think about. The reason this is
done is that zeroing out an array has a cost and so by default for this to be as optimal as
possible it doesn't zero out those pieces of data. Generally that's not going to be a problem but
again if you need to switch to the kind of safer mode you can do so. So what this looks like is
here for example imagine we have a method it's going to be called by some type loop as processing
is being done and it needs a temporary buffer that it's going to pass into another method.
So here we're allocating each time the thousand bytes for this buffer. We can very easily
switch that to instead prefer using the shared array pool and renting a thousand. Now the main
difference here is that when we then want to work with that buffer we now have to pass in the
actual length so that we know we only get we're going to only work with a thousand elements which
is the piece that we know we're going to populate it because typically if we rent one thousand the
minimum size that array pool can give us is one oh two four bytes and it might even be larger if
there's none of those available in it moves a size up and so it doesn't mean that when we're working
with the data below we have to then slice into it for the length that we actually know we've populated
in the previous method. We do need to remember to return the array for the pool to have any real
benefit. I'm showing it here with a tri-finally Microsoft have actually moved away from this guidance
fairly recently and tend not to bother with it so the idea of doing it in a tri-finally is you always
guarantee if there's an exception in that other method we're returning the array to the pool but
actually the cost of doing a tri-finally and the operations needed is usually not necessary for
the number of times that might actually cause an exception so unless that method could really
cause an exception very often it's better to just do the method that you want and then return it
afterwards and on the few cases where an exception were to occur it doesn't matter if that buffer
doesn't go back into the pool it will eventually for its finalizer by collected by GC anyway so
it's up to you it doesn't really matter either way I still sometimes do it this way to just to protect myself
so the other type I want to show is system IO pipelines this one's good if you ever work with like
streaming data or sort of data coming across the wire and so this was originally created by the ASP
net team I think it was pretty much David Fowler's kind of child that he sort of built into the
dot net system so it was originally in the ASP net code base and then has been shifted into the
runtime code base and the key reason it was kind of introduced was around Kestrel so Kestrel is
the web server in ASP net core it's obviously dealing with lots of bytes coming off a wire that
then go through the ASP net core pipeline internally and one of the things the team wanted to do was
trying to avoid all of those costs of switching between different streams as that data gets processed
through the pipeline so they found that by moving to this new sort of pipelines library they could
roughly improve their performance by about 2x in the kind of Kestrel scenario and typically it's
just done by removing what would otherwise be code you could write yourself to manage streams and
temporary buffers and use the array pool to try and avoid allocations but it would actually have a
lot of boilerplate and edge cases that you'd have to consider so it just wraps that all up for you
and does all of the heavy lifting so the main difference is that unlike when you're using streams
yourself with pipelines it's managing those buffers for you so you don't create the the buffers that
you'd pass in as you're processing the stream you just work with this pipe concept and internally
it's using what's known as a memory pool which basically is backed by an array pool behind the scenes
to actually manage those buffers without allocating. Two ends to a pipe as you might guess so there's
a writing end and when we write as a few ways we can do it there are sort of shortcut methods for
writing small blocks of data directly with write or write async or in most scenarios what you might
want to do is actually just ask the pipe for a block of memory in this case it comes back as a
memory of byte that you can then populate so it's a memory of byte typically because pipelines is
going to be used in these async scenarios where you're getting data off of IO network connections
etc but of course you can switch from that memory of byte to a non async method at any point
and start working with that same data as a span. Once you've worked with some of the data you just
advance the pipe right by how much you've written and then flush it and as soon as you flush it
that awakens the reading end that will be sitting there waiting so on the reader we called read async
and that will then just asynchronously await data being available from the pipe so it's non-blocking
and eventually we get back a read result once the data is flushed in for us we can access the buffer
on that read result which comes back as this read only sequence of byte so wire sequence down here
in a memory on the way in and the reason is ahead of time the pipe doesn't know how much data is going
to fill it typically if you're reading off of the wire for example then you might be dealing with
chunk data and you don't know the content length yet and so what it does internally is it will
rent a block of memory and start filling it for you and if you're keeping up with the reading
and the writing then that might be sufficient but if at any point the reading end slows down and
isn't actually processing all of that block in time then it will just rent another block of memory
and then another block of memory and keep filling it and then on the reading end what it gives you is
essentially a linked list of those blocks of memory as this read only sequence and gives us a way
to view that data in the correct sequence so the example that sort of demonstrates usage of this
again similar to the last one same sort of microservice we were dealing with retrieving objects
from s3 in this case it was a tab separated file so we wanted to get free columns of data from
separated file and index them into elastic search so I shall show you the before code
I didn't write this I'm going to tell you that in advance because you might spot the problems
so this is roughly what the original code was doing so here I'm using a file stream in this
demo app but it was basically an s3 stream from the s3 API instead it needed to be decompressed
because it was zipped gzipped for decompression and then this is where the code gets a bit interesting
so it then after decompressing it creates a new memory stream and it copies from the decompressed
stream into the memory stream it then calls to array to get the entire bytes from that memory stream
and then called get string to then get the string representation of that file and then it was
passing it into this parser thing now the reason it was doing that I think at the time is that it was
using this library called tiny csv parser that I think only took string inputs at one point
at least that's the explanation I was given and I will trust the engineer did this for a good reason
but if you're looking at this code you can probably spot where this might allocate we're copying
memory we are creating a new array which again is copying we're getting a string that represents
the entire contents of a large file so all of these allocations that occur here also occur on the
large object heap because typically these files were about a thousand ten thousand rows each time
so the new code that we switched to slightly more complex if you look at the length compared to
the last one but what we did instead was we still need the decompressed stream but as soon as we've
got that we get the users pipe reader create here to just create a reader over that stream so that
gives us a pipe reader that's accessing the stream as the data becomes available and so we do the
read async we access the buffer and as soon as we've got the buffer we can call paths lines to see
what lines we've got and so this is dealing with that read only sequence that was coming off the pipe
reader and it uses a sequence reader as a helper type that allows us to more easily parse through
these sequences because we have to deal with a scenario that we might have one block of memory or
multiple blocks that we have to work through so the sequence reader deals with that and so it gives
us this convenience that we can just loop through the reader until we've read everything we can try and
read out an entire line so what we want to essentially get is one line of the file
delimited by the new line so if it finds a new line give me the span of that file or of that line
that represents the data that I can then process with paths line down below and then paths line is
just manually doing what that tiny see as fee paths the library was doing where it's basically
accessing the free tabs or columns of data that we actually care about so it basically
finds the index of the tab character checks if that current tab count that we're at is a piece of
data that we care about and if it is at that point it does get the string by slicing the line
from the current position to where that tab appears and that gets us our string that we need to
populate our objects going to elastic search so it only does that for the three columns we care
about 0, 1 and 10 and as soon as we reach that we actually then just break out of this loop because
we're not going to go past the columns that we care about when we're reading that line that's
pretty much what it does and I'll show you the before and after of that so that's just switching to
those pipelines and again spam based optimizations so the original code versus the new code about 81
percent quicker we weren't going for speed the reason we investigated this service was that it was
running as a container we had memory limits set on it and quite regularly it was hitting those
memory limits and killing the container and so we constantly seem to find ourselves increasing the
the container limits of that container and that's why we looked at it we saw that code and we
then realized that actually by switching to this new version we could remove 97 percent of the
allocations just by switching to something that wasn't allocating as much and when I did a profile
on that it was about 2.85 of that with the data that we actually needed the strings that we did
want to push into elastic search so there was about 0.45 negative overhead some of that comes from
the pipe reader types and the sequence reader types I did I still do want to check and see if I can
get that down any lower but this is a good example of like sometimes stopping when it you've done
enough is perfectly fine we'd solve the main problem that 0.45 negative overhead is insignificant
compared to the problem we started with and so we didn't feel that need to go any further with this
one so we've got a few minutes left so I'll very quickly try and go over the system text
j's of stuff with a quick demo of what that can do for your code so these have been in the box
since don't call free oh so traditionally most people will probably be familiar with new soft
json for doing json parsing Microsoft introduced this is in in the box API in free oh to start giving us
new version of json parsing that could take advantage of these new high performance techniques
and so it gives us free levels to work with we can work at a very low level with directly with
some kind of uTF8 bytes for the json reader and writer we can work at a middle-level when we're
reading using this json document object model that we can then process our way through in a
kind of read forward fashion and then we also have a regular kind of serializer where you can just say
give give me an object and serialize it or give me some json and d serialize it into an object
even that new higher level one is going to be more optimal than using new soft json just because
it tries to avoid allocations behind the scenes as much as possible but the real gains come if you
really need them from those low level types so the example I have for this again similar scenario
to the last one I was working on a scenario where we were bulk indexing some data into elastic
search when you do that with elastic search it gives you a response back that tells you did any of
the maybe hundred one thousand whatever it is you're sending in operations the indexing operations
have an error and if and then it also gives you a summary for each operation as to what the
status codes were for them so what we wanted to do is just find out if any of the data we tried to
index was failing so that we could track the IDs and essentially dead letter those items and deal
with them later so I'll give you a quick tour of the before and after code so the original code
is really terse it was using new use and source json that's all the code there is
ultimately it was getting to the point where we had a json serializer decerializing the
json response that comes back into this type which has the length of time it took whether or not
there were errors and then for each item each indexing operation what was the result
and then what we do is check that errors property and if there's no errors it's given us a force
on that errors property then we can just say that yes this was successful and there's no IDs to
return otherwise we have to process those items to find the IDs of the ones that failed so that
is pretty easy code now the new code I'll grant you is a good example of where moving to the
higher performance code is less terse and this would be less maintainable right but if you need
the performance then this is the kind of thing you might end up doing so what this does that's
different is we read a stream in this case directly and we go into this parse errors where we've
read some data off the stream we just use the rented array from the array pool for that buffer
for the streaming in this case and so what we do here is we switch to that low level json reader type
and at that point what we can do is basically ask it to read through the the bytes that it's received
giving us each json token as we reach it so this reads forward a json token at a time
but we track a bunch of states so you can see I'm passing in a bunch of my own state in here
mostly as by reference as well as this json reader state object which allows us to make that
a utfa json reader re-enterable so the state tracks where it is in that json structure so if you're
getting data in chunks off of the wire you can start processing the json and then return to this
method later on to continue with the next chunk and the basic premise of what this code does is it
switches on the json token and so I can kind of track my way through that that expected json data
I'm getting so am I into into the start object am I into the array have I reached certain properties so does the token
value text of the string match this predefined in this case this u8 here basically converts this string
literal into a utfa json byte as a read-only span again using that same technique to kind of cash
those in the binary and so what this does is basically track when we've read the ID properties
and the status properties of that item checks if we've read like a true or false result for example
and the key really is down here that when once we've checked that errors property on the message
and if it's false either there's no errors we can stop processing the rest of this json data
and so even further up the code here we do another check and we break out of this other
while loop here as we're reading that data through the off the stream so we can short circuit in the
happy path where we generally expect all items to have been indexed successfully and that's kind
of the crux of the improvement there I'll show you the numbers before we switch to the last couple of slides
so in the unhappy path where there are errors on the response then we still see that there's a 67
percent reduction in execution time and still a very good reduction in the overhead of the json
passing we still have some allocations because we need to capture all of those IDs of the failed
messages or the failed operations and so that that means we've saved 84 percent but not
completely saved our allocations but for the 99 percent case where we expect everything to be
indexed successfully because of that early exiting as we've read the first few tokens of json which
is roughly the first I think 20 something bytes of json data we exit really early so now we've
we've exited in 200 nanoseconds from that processing loop and we've got zero allocations now because
that sort of success path there's nothing to gather we don't actually need to allocate any
instances of objects to track their data and so very quickly we can get some real gains with that
utfh json reading approach so to wrap up in the last minute or two maybe you like what you've
seen today and you want to go and get business buying how do you do that I recommend starting with
quick wins so think of services you know have performance issues within your organization people
complain how long they take or how much have any instances you have to run to process your data
that kind of thing then use a scientific approach to work out the gains and then change that
into a monetary value so the main problem we're going to a business owner and saying hey I can
remove all byte allocations on this code path is that business owners probably don't really care
what that means or might not understand but if you show the monetary value it tends to make a
bigger difference so give them a cost of benefit ratio so all of the stuff I've shown you today plus
other techniques went into one key microservice we had that one that was dealing with 18 million
messages a day and through various experiments with these small changes worked out we could save
about half of the allocation and roughly double the per instance throughput of those processing
services and what that led to is reducing one vm a year that we needed to run that particular
microservices a container now $1,700 on its own might will be worth the engineering effort that
it took to introduce this but we had hundreds of microservices doing very similar things and we
could reapply this pattern and so this then can start to scale so these kind of gains can really
have an impact as you move to multiple instances where you're applying these same kind of techniques
over and over again so in summary when you're doing this kind of stuff don't assume don't make
assumptions measure with profiling tools measure with benchmarking before and after doing things
be scientific so small changes each time have a theory validate the theory and move on focus on
the hot paths because they're the areas that you're going to get the most gain from don't copy memory
so using things like span to just slice your way into existing memories a very good way of reducing
allocation overhead do use a raples where it's appropriate to do so to avoid those short live
buffer type allocations if you're doing anything with sort of regular streaming of data then
and off no come on and yeah consider system text json apis is a quick swap out for new and soft
json for some wins if you want to go deeper this book by conrad there's a new addition coming
this year i highly recommend it it's about that thick it's about thousand pages in english it's
fantastic to read and it's also great to carry around as a weapon and it has all of the stuff i've
shown you today and more so that's it i'll give you the link to the slides i don't have time for
questions but i'm happy to kind of answer them off to the side afterwards thank you